# Niklas Baier



Munich, Germany



niklas.baier@yahoo.de



niklasbaier.github.io/me



linkedin.com/niklasbaier github.com/niklasbaier



# M.Sc. Student in Management & Technology at the Technical University of Munich, Certified Financial Investment Specialist (CCI) for open-end funds.

Practical experience from asset management, banking, consulting, and honorary board membership. International and open mindset, hands-on-mentality, as well as a passion for quantitative finance.

## **ACADEMIC EDUCATION**

10/2019 - approx. **Technical University of Munich** Munich, Germany 09/2022 M.Sc. Management & Technology, preliminary grade of 1.5/1.0 Major in Finance & Accounting (Asset Management, Behavioral Finance, Capital Markets Law, Derivatives, International Capital Markets & Investment Practice, Private Equity) Minor in Informatics (Adv. Databases, Blockchain Engineering, Fundamentals of AI / ML / DL) Awardee of 'TUMfast (TUM Finance & Accounting Selected Talents)' scholarship 10/2014 - 09/2019 **Technical University of Munich** Munich, Germany B.Sc. Management & Technology, final grade of 2.0/1.0 Major in Finance & Accounting (Corporate Finance, Cost Accounting, Financial Accounting & Reporting, Investment & Financial Management) Minor in Informatics (Fundamentals of Informatics / Programming / Software Engineering / Databases / Operating Systems / Document Engineering) B.Sc. Engineering Science (change of study after the 2<sup>nd</sup> semester) 08/2006 - 07/2014 Municipal High School 'Werner-von-Siemens' Munich, Germany General A-levels, final grade of 1.0/1.0 (Laureate) **International Experience** 06/2021 - 07/2021 Università Bocconi Online Summer School, Equity & Venture Capital Financing (6 ECTS), GPA 4.0/4.0 06/2020 - 07/2020 **HFC Paris** Online Summer School, Investment Banking & International Finance (7 ECTS), GPA 4.0/4.0 **Tohoku University** 10/2017 - 03/2018 Sendai, Japan Exchange Semester, International Program of Liberal Arts (30 ECTS), GPA 4.0/4.0 Courses about Japanese Language / Culture / Communication & Work Behavior, and Karate

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

**Ouantumrock** 01/2022 - approx. Grünwald, Germany 04/2022 Quantitative Strategy Research, Project Student Factor Momentum and Mean Reversion in Multifactor Investing 11/2018 - 08/2021 BayernLB (Bavarian State Bank) Munich, Germany Credit Service Real Estate & Structured Finance, Working Student

Awardee of 'JASSO (Japan Student Services Organization)' scholarship

Buyer processing in the area of property development financing; preparation of guarantees, lien releases, in rem rights, and loan coverages; audition of insurance contracts and lease agreements; commissioning of construction progress assessments

## Business Management Mid Office, Working Student

Assistance for the division's functional and performance analysis; decentralized business continuity management; audit coordination; internal control system; market research; conception of a migration strategy for the internal task controlling to MS Dynamics CRM

## Project Management Officer for the digitization project 'DEAP', Working Student

Preparation and follow-up of committee meetings; organization of project dates and workshops; administrative and technical support for the project team

03/2018 - 05/2018 **KPMG Germany** Munich, Germany

Consulting - Data & Trend Analytics, Intern

Derivation, condensation and quantification of trends from weak signals using semantic data analysis and the KPMG Research Cloud

## EXTRACURRICULAR ACTIVITIES

#### 03/2017 - 01/2021

### ACO Charity e.V. (formerly 'Asia Charity Organization (ACO) e.V.')

Munich, Germany

- Non-profit association consisting of approx. 80 members (donations of > 60,000€)
- Development of sustainable educational projects for socially disadvantaged children and teenagers (esp. in Vietnam), youth development of own members

#### Head of Treasury & Board Member (Internal Affairs), Tenure for 2020

- Successful steering of the association through the COVID pandemic and the accompanying cancellation of previous annual benefit events through alternative sources of financing, digital teaching offers, virtual fundraising events, marketing and special motivation of the members
- Administration of donations and membership fees, handling of payment transactions, bookkeeping and preparation of cash reports
- Co-initiation, project management and active teaching within the framework of 'ACO Tandem' (online English lessons for students of ethnic minorities of the aid project 'Future through Education' in Vietnam)

#### Team Leader Finance for the event 'Taste of Asia 2018'

- Leadership & coordination of the team members; budgeting & controlling of the other teams
- Planning of the cash register system & implementation of a donation live tracking system

#### since 10/2016

#### **TUM School of Management**

Munich, Germany

- Ambassador for the faculty and its bachelor program at schools and partner universities at home and abroad
- Buddy for incoming exchange students

## **FURTHER EDUCATION & CERTIFICATIONS**

08/2021	National Taiwan University  Machine Learning Summer School 2021 Taipei	Online
06/2021	Chamber of Commerce and Industry for Munich and Upper Bavaria Munich, Certified Financial Investment Specialist (open-end funds, §34f Abs. 1 Ziff. 1 GewO)	Germany
10/2020	Bloomberg LP Bloomberg Market Concepts	Online
04/2020	University of Helsinki Elements of Al (2 ECTS)	Online
MOOCs	<ul> <li>Options Trading Strategies in Python (Quantra, 11/2021)</li> <li>Python for Trading: Basic (Quantra, 09/2021)</li> <li>Automate the Boring Stuff with Python Programming (Udemy, 09/2021)</li> <li>LaTeX for Professional Publications (Udemy, 05/2020)</li> <li>The Complete Financial Analyst Training &amp; Investing Course (Udemy, 08/2019)</li> </ul>	

# **SKILLS & INTERESTS**

Programming &	
Software Engineeri	ng

- C, Java (advanced)
  - Git & GitHub, Agile Project Management (SCRUM, Jira, Confluence) (basic)

**Data Science &** Artificial Intelligence

- Python (numpy, pandas, matplotlib, etc.) (advanced), R (basic)
- PyTorch (Lightning) (basic)

Big Data & **Databases** 

- SQL, Datalog, XPath & XQuery, SPARQL (basic)
- MySQL (basic)

Web Development

Wordpress (basic)

Other

Blockchain: Solidity (basic) Documents: LaTeX (basic)

**Business Software** 

- Microsoft Office (advanced)
- Excel VBA & Power Pivot (basic)
- Bloomberg Terminal & Thomson Reuters (basic)

Languages

German (native), English (fluent, DAAD C2), French (intermediate), Japanese (basic)

Interests & **Hobbies** 

- Quantitative Finance, Algorithmic Trading, Artificial Intelligence, Virtual Reality, PC Hardware Reading (esp. self-improvement, personal finance, Wall Street, technology & science-fiction), Fitness training, Blogging, Playing the guitar, DJing

CV version as of 02/2022.

Testimonials and certificates upon request.